Okay בוקר טוב. Boker tov. So today we pick up on נו
עמוד ב, Nun Vav Amud Bet, 56B, the משנה, Mishnah, and let's
give it a and we will God willing wrap up this פרק
perek and begin the next one.
So the end of this פרק perek is a lot easier than
the whole bulk of the פרק. perek. We just went through all
these variations about טומאה tumah and what type of טומאת המת tumas
hamet a נזיר Nazir is מגולח megaleach on it, certain scenarios like
of a מצורע metzora or other types of טומאה tumah that are
טומאת מת, tumas meit, even biblical טומאת מת, tumas meit, but that
he does not we have a מסורה mesorah that he does not
shave as a result and still there's some of those the מצורע
metzora case and some of those cases of טומאת מת tumas meit
of a corpse טומאה tumah where he does not shave are ones
where nevertheless he can't count those days towards his נזירות. nezirut. We
now pick up with two interesting משניות mishnayot that are not as
intense. Let's take a look.
אמר רבי אליעזר משום רבי יהושע, Amar Rabbi Eliezer mishum Rabbi Yehoshua,
said Rabbi Eliezer in the name of Rabbi
Yehoshua, כל טומאה מן המת שהנזיר מגולח עליה אין חייבין עליה על
ביאת
מקדש.
kol tumah min hameit shehanazir megaleach aleha ein chayavin aleha
al
biat mikdash.
Oh, I'm sorry, חייבים עליה, chayavim aleha, thank you, good catch, see
if you were paying attention. כל טומאה מן המת שהנזיר מגולח עליה
חייבים עליה על ביאת מקדש וכל טומאה מן המת שאין הנזיר מגולח
עליה אין חייבים עליה על ביאת מקדש. kol tumah min hameit shehanazir
megaleach aleha chayavim aleha al biat mikdash vechol tumah min hameit she'ein
hanazir megaleach aleha ein chayavim aleha al biat mikdash. Okay, so that's
what. So these טומות tumot of the dead that a נזיר Nazir
shaves his head for and that destroys the earlier נזירות, nezirut, these
are the ones that if you are טמא מת tamei meit of
this nature and you enter into the בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash you
are חייב chayav for violating entering into the בית המקדש בטומאה, Beit
Hamikdash betumah, but if it is a טומאה מן המת tumah min
hameit that a נזיר Nazir does not shave
you do not transgress violating entering into בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash even
if you are טמא מת tamei meit as a result of these
טומות. tumot. אמר רבי מאיר לא תהא זו קלה מן השרץ. Amar
Rabbi Meir lo tehei zu kallah min hasheretz. Rabbi Meir says whoa,
if you for entering into בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash when you are
טמא, tamei, and we're talking here now because interestingly to remind you
טומאת מת tumas meit is allowed even in מחנה לויה, Machaneh Leviyah,
even in עזרת נשים, Ezrat Nashim, right up to the actual עזרה.
Azarah. So the only what we're talking about is entering into the
temple grounds itself, entering into the עזרה. Azarah. So that you're חייב
chayav any type of טומאה, tumah, טומאת מת, tumas meit, טומאת שרץ,
tumas sheretz, anything. So Rabbi Meir's response back is he says look,
maybe this is some type of a lighter טומאת מת tumas meit
that doesn't have the consequence of a נזיר Nazir having to reverse
himself, but it's certainly no lighter than touching a rodent. We're talking
about טמא מת tamei meit for God's sake, so how could you
say that you're not חייב chayav by entering into the בית המקדש.
Beit Hamikdash. Now obviously if it was one of those דרבנן's d'rabbanans
like שכוכות ופרעות sechochot u'praot and so on, בית הפרס, Beit Hapras,
nobody was debating that. But we're talking about those that are assumed
to be
דאורייתא, d'oraita, biblical, and nevertheless there's a rule that for some reason
it doesn't destroy the נזירות. nezirut. But he says okay, but you're
still טמא tamei and any type of טומאה tumah you violate when
you enter into the בית המקדש. Beit Hamikdash. So let's take a
look what the גמרא Gemara says about this. דרבי אליעזר משום רבי
יהושע גמרא לה. D'Rabbi Eliezer mishum Rabbi Yehoshua gemara lah. So now
the גמרא Gemara is interested in it's not the משנה Mishnah at
all really the substance of it, just really a side point, like
here in the משנה Mishnah he says it in the name of
Rabbi Yehoshua. דרבי אליעזר משום רבי יהושע גמרא לה, D'Rabbi Eliezer mishum
Rabbi Yehoshua gemara lah, this link to נזיר מגולח Nazir megaleach and
חייב chayav for entering בית המקדש. Beit Hamikdash. דמשום רבי יהושע בר
ממא גמרא לה. Demishum Rabbi Yehoshua bar Mama gemara lah. It wasn't
in the name of Rabbi Yehoshua, and the
סתם stam Rabbi Yehoshua is Rabbi Yehoshua ben Chananya. But we know
from another source that he learns it from Rabbi Yehoshua bar Mama.
דתניא דתנן בברייתא. De'tanya de'tenan be'vraita. אמר רבי אליעזר, Amar Rabbi Eliezer,
said Rabbi Eliezer, כשהלכתי לארדסקייא, Keshehalachti l'Ardaskaya, when I went to Ardaskaya,
I have no idea where that is,
מצאתי את רבי יהושע בן פתר ראש, matzati et Rabbi Yehoshua ben
Peter Rosh, Rabbi Yehoshua the son of Peter Rosh, that was his
father's name or his surname. שהיה יושב ודן לפני רבי מאיר בהלכה.
shehayah yoshev vedan lifnei Rabbi Meir behalacha. There are three Rabbi Yehoshuas
here just to fully confuse you.
He was sitting and debating or discussing his analysis
in the presence of Rabbi Meir. And here is what he said:
כל טומאה מן המת שהנזיר מגולח עליה חייבין עליה משום ביאת מקדש
וכל טומאה מן המת שאין הנזיר מגולח עליה אין חייבין עליה משום
ביאת מקדש. kol tumah min hameit shehanazir megaleach aleha chayavin aleha mishum
biat mikdash vechol tumah min hameit she'ein hanazir megaleach aleha ein chayavin
aleha mishum biat mikdash. And this is what he was saying to
Rabbi Meir, that
any טומאה tumah that is of the מת meit that causes a
נזיר Nazir to shave and that destroys the נזירות nezirut you would
be חייב chayav if you were that טמא tamei and you enter
the בית המקדש, Beit Hamikdash, but if it's one of those exceptions
to a נזיר מגולח Nazir megaleach it's also an exception to entering
into the בית המקדש, Beit Hamikdash, same type of
an
exception of a ruling with an exception. Anyway, so the גמרא Gemara
says amar, that's what he said to him. אמר לו, Amar lo,
Rabbi Meir said back to this Rabbi Yehoshua ben Peter Rosh, אמר
לו לא תהא זו קלה מן השרץ, amar lo lo tehei zu
kallah min hasheretz, it should not be lighter than just touching a
rodent, and again Rabbi Meir says in our משנה. Mishnah. Okay, so
that's his response to this. This is now a teaching of Rabbi
Yehoshua ben Peter Rosh.
Dead rodent, touching a dead rodent. אמרתי לו, Amarti lo, now I.
But now here the speaker of this is רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer,
okay, who came and saw this exchange happening, אמרתי לו, Amarti lo,
I said to him, presumably to רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, who gave
this push back, כמה אתה בקי ברבי יהושע בר ממא? Kama ata
baki b'Rabbi Yehoshua bar Mama? Are you familiar with רבי יהושע בר
ממא? Rabbi Yehoshua bar Mama? Do you know how a weighty authority
he is? אמר לי הין, Amar li hein, Rabbi Meir said yes.
So I then, רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, said to רבי מאיר, Rabbi
Meir, כך אמר לי רבי יהושע בר ממא, Kach amar li Rabbi
Yehoshua bar Mama, here’s what Rabbi Yehoshua bar Mama said, משום רבי
יהושע, mishum Rabbi Yehoshua, in the name of רבי יהושע, Rabbi Joshua,
this would be the רבי יהושע בן חנניה. Rabbi Yehoshua ben Chananya.
שמעתי שכל טומאה מן המת שנזיר מגלח עליה חייבין עליה משום ביאת
מקדש וכל טומאה מן המת שאין נזיר מגלח עליה אין חייבין עליה
משום ביאת מקדש. Shamati shekol tumah min hamet shenazir megaleach aleha chayavin
aleha mishum biat mikdash vechol tumah min hamet she’ein nazir megaleach aleha
ein chayavin aleha mishum biat mikdash. I have this tradition from רבי
יהושע בר ממא Rabbi Yehoshua bar Mama who says it in the
name of רבי יהושע Rabbi Joshua that yes, there’s a similar exception
for ביאת מקדש biat mikdash and backing up the position here of
this other רבי יהושע, Rabbi Joshua, רבי יהושע בן פטרוז. Rabbi Yehoshua
ben Petaroz. Okay, so that’s what I said to רבי מאיר. Rabbi
Meir. I have this tradition. Yes, it is true. This is an
exception to this הלכה halacha as well. אמרו, Amru, so now, so
anyway, that was all very fascinating, gave a little bit more color
to that. But the thing is that now we see that רבי
אליעזר's Rabbi Eliezer tradition is from רבי יהושע בר ממא Rabbi Yehoshua
bar Mama who received it from רבי יהושע. Rabbi Joshua. So why
in our משנה mishna does it say רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says
in the name of רבי יהושע Rabbi Joshua if the most immediate
authority he received it from was רבי יהושע בר ממא? Rabbi Yehoshua
bar Mama? Right, he only sort
of grandfathered received it from רבי יהושע. Rabbi Joshua. All right, so
let’s see what the גמרא Gemara says. So שמע מינה, Shma mina,
from the fact that it jumps over the middle position in this
tradition, we hear from this: כל שמעתתא דמיתאמרה בבי תלתא, Kol shma’teta
d’mitamra b’bei tlata, if there was a tradition that was said over
three, transmitted through three generations, you know, or, you know, whatever, through,
A gave to B gave to C... בי תלתא, bei tlata, kind
of three,
that's not what it means in this context. קדמיה ובתרייא אמרינן, Kadmaya
ubatraya amrinan, when we repeat the tradition, we say the person who
was the last person to report it and the person who originated
it, the first and the last. מצעייא לא אמרינן, Metzaya la amrinan,
but we don't always have to say, you know, all the middle
steps of how that tradition got to this final reporting... but we
don't always have
the same first name.
Well, that's why we didn't say it, maybe. Anyway, okay. So that's
why רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says it who got it eventually from
רבי יהושע. Rabbi Joshua. One degree removed, but he got it from
רבי יהושע. Rabbi Joshua. We don't have to list all the steps.
אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק, Amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak, אנן נמי
תנינא, anan nami tanina, I’ll tell you a similar example to this
where we skip some of the middle steps. אמר נחום הלבלר Amar
Nachum HaLavlur says, כך מקובלני מרבי מיאשא שקיבל מאבא שקיבל מן הזוגות
שקיבלו מן הנביאים. kach mikubalni miRabbi Mayasha shekibel me’abba shekibel min hazugot
shekiblu min hanevi’im. This is the tradition I have from רבי מיאשא
Rabbi Mayasha who received it from his father, who received it from
the זוגות, zugot, from you know, the early pairs of rabbinic authorities
in the time of the second בית המקדש, Beit HaMikdash, like הלל
ושמאי Hillel veShammai and those that came before them, שקיבלו מן הנביאים,
shekiblu min hanevi’im, and they received this tradition back from the prophets.
הלכה למשה מסיני, Halacha l’Moshe miSinai, all the way going back to
משה רבינו. Moshe Rabbeinu. הזורע שבת וחרדל Hazorea shevet vechardal בשנים ושלשה
מקומות, bishnayim u’shlosha mekomot,
if you plant שבת shevet and חרדל, chardal, which חרדל chardal is
mustard seed, I don't know what שבת shevet is.
Dill. Dill and mustard seed in two and three different locations in
your field, שנותנין פאה מכל אחד ואחד, shenotnin pe’ah mikol echad ve’eachad,
you give a, you leave a corner from each different section, not
just one corner on everything. So we won't unpack that. It has
a lot to do with הלכות פאה. hilchot pe’ah. But that's what
he said. That's my tradition. And תוספות Tosafot says that's not always
true, depends whether you gathered it in in one time or you
sort of, or you made multiple, or different stages you gathered in
the crops. But whatever it is, that's my tradition that you give
two or three times, that you give for each different section. Now,
all we're interested in is the way he speaks about the chain
of tradition. ויהושע וכלב לא קא חשיב. V’Yehoshua veKalev lo ka chashiv.
Look, he gave every generation, okay, as it were, but he went
from the נביאים nevi’im to משה. Moshe. What about, you know, how
about what we say in
פרקי אבות? Pirkei Avot? משה קיבל תורה מסיני ומסרה ליהושע ויהושע לזקנים
וזקנים לנביאים. Moshe kibel Torah miSinai u’mesarah liYehoshua v’Yehoshua lizkenim uzkenim l’nevi’im.
So he left off the generation of the יהושע Yehoshua and the
זקנים. zkenim. So clearly you see you don't have to say every
middle stage. Now, of course he does say some of the middle
stages. Anyway, it's not necessary to say every middle stage, שמע מינה.
shma mina. That's what we get from that. Okay. So you could
say, if you say a long list, you can skip a little
bit. But יהושע Yehoshua at least maybe you should say everything. Yes,
Charlie.
I have two questions. Wasn't רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer a contemporary and
a disputant of רבי יהושע בן חנניה? Rabbi Yehoshua ben Chananya?
Yeah, so that is true. I was actually wondering about that because
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua are also contemporaries,
actually both teachers of רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva.
But, you know, so it is possible that you receive the tradition
like second-hand, third-hand, even from through a contemporary. But it would be
very funny that if this is your contemporary and colleague that you
can't ask the person
directly, you know.
So maybe this is after he was put in חרם? cherem?
I don't know. It's, but it is a very good, I was
wondering the same thing, that רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and רבי יהושע
Rabbi Yehoshua are contemporaries, and here we have him getting it three
generations removed as—I mean, whatever, like not directly from רבי יהושע. Rabbi
Joshua. I should say, by the way, that the interesting thing that's
not in our משנה, mishna, that as we've been talking, I've been
saying to you the entire פרק perek that's in מסכת שמחות Masechet
Smachot and is much more relevant למעשה l’ma’aseh is כל טומאה שאין
הנזיר מגלח עליה... kol tumah she’ein hanazir megaleach aleha... אין כהן Kohen.
מוזהר עליו *ein kohein muzhar alav*. So that a כהן Kohen *kohein*,
if it's the things that a נזיר Nazir *nazir* does not have
to shave as a result, a כהן kohen *kohein* is not biblically,
is not considered a biblical transgression and
sometimes maybe even not transgression at all that gets to the whole
question that we mentioned about חרב כחלל *cherev k'chalal* and the כלים
הנוגעים במת *keilim hanoge'im b'meit*. Are there some exceptions here to טומאת
כהנים Kohanim *tum'at kohanim* is also an important question, yes.
Same question that this particular הלכה halakha, *halacha*. Silks after vegetables do
not stain and normally don't do פאה *pe'ah* I
should say, which is kind of a strange,
but I'm
not going to unpack that here. Let's take a look at the
next משנה mishna *mishnah*. Now next משנה mishna *mishnah* also has another
discussion about where we learn these הלכות *halachot* from. It's funny, a
lot of הלכות *halachot* of נזיר Nazir? *nazir* are just הלכה halakha
*halacha*. If you remember some of the debates of ר' יוחנן *Rabbi
Yochanan* and ריש לקיש *Resh Lakish*, ר' יוחנן *Rabbi Yochanan* would say
הלכה halakha, היא בנזיר *Halacha hi b'Nazir*. A lot of these exceptions
seem pretty arbitrary. Why is a נזיר Nazir *nazir* not מגלח megalei'ach,
*megaleach* if it's real טומאה tuma *tuma*? And now we get to
actually some an interesting debate here or discussion between ר' עקיבא Akiva,
*Rabbi Akiva* and his רבי Rabbi *Rebbi*, ר' אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer*. אמר
ר' עקיבא דנתי לפני ר' אליעזר *Amar Rabbi Akiva: Danti lifnei Rabbi
Eliezer*. The same phrase, remember ר' יהושע *Rabbi Yehoshua* we said before
בן פטורש *Ben Patarosh* was דן לפני ר' מאיר *dan lifnei Rabbi
Meir*, which sort of means I laid out my argument or my
position in front of him and this was the discussion we had.
דנתי לפני ר' אליעזר *Danti lifnei Rabbi Eliezer*, so I discussed this
issue in front of ר' אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer*. מה מעצם כשעורה שאינו
מטמא אדם באהל הנזיר מגלח megalei'ach על מגעו ועל משאו *Ma me-etzem
kase'ora she'eino metamei adam b'ohel, hanazir megaleach al maga'o v'al masa'o*. When
you get to a bone, a tiny little bone the size of
a barley grain, it does not cause טומאה tuma. באהל *tuma b'ohel*,
and a נזיר Nazir *nazir* nevertheless, it's weighty enough that a נזיר
Nazir *nazir* would shave if he touched or moved it and would
destroy the נזירות nezirut. *nezirut*. So רביעית דם Revi'is dam *revi'it dam*,
a quarter of a לוג log *log* of blood שהוא מטמא אדם
באהל *shehu metamei adam b'ohel*, is powerful enough that it causes טומאה
tumah *tuma* of a person in an אהל *ohel*, even biblically. ואינו
דין שיהא נזיר מגלח nazir megalei'ach, עליו על מגעו ועל משאו *Ve'eino
din she-ya-nazir megaleach alav al maga'o v'al masa'o*? How much more so
should a נזיר Nazir *nazir* have to shave if he touched it
or moved it? Because what did we say? What's the minimum amount
for a נזיר Nazir *nazir* to have to shave by blood? Do
you remember? חצי לוג chatzi log *Chatzi log*. No, for a נזיר
nazir *nazir* to have to shave is a חצי לוג chatzi log.
*chatzi log*. So ר' עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* says why do you demand
a חצי לוג chatzi log *chatzi log*? We should רביעית revi'is לוג
log *revi'it log* should be enough. I'll make a קל וחומר kal
vachomer. *kal vachomer*. Now if I wanted to say how much if
he's only in the same... Notice ר' עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* says a
נזיר nazir *nazir* should shave על מגעו ועל משאו *al maga'o v'al
masa'o*. He doesn't say being in the same אהל *ohel* because that's
not a good קל וחומר kal vachomer. *kal vachomer*. Because the bone,
the little piece of bone, is only through touch and moving. But
he says if this little piece of bone, which doesn't cause טומאה
tumah *tuma* in the אהל *ohel*, is powerful enough that a נזיר
nazir *nazir* will have to shave, then a רביעית revi'is? *revi'it* לוג
*log* of blood should certainly if you touch it, it shouldn't be
worse than touching a little piece of bone, because a רביעית revi'is
*revi'it* לוג *log* of blood is enough to cause טומאה tumah. באהל
*tuma b'ohel*. Whether you need a higher standard for a נזיר nazir
*nazir* for טומאת אהל *tum'at ohel*, maybe you do. Maybe you'll need
a חצי לוג *chatzi log* for טומאת אהל *tum'at ohel*. But for
touching, if a tiny little chip of bone is enough, why should
a רביעית revi'is *revi'it* of blood not be enough? A רביעית revi'is
*revi'it* of blood causes טומאה tumah באהל *tuma b'ohel*. Very reasonable argument.
So he's not arguing again for it to cause באהל *b'ohel* that
you should have to shave for a רביעית revi'is *revi'it* of blood,
but for God's sake just touching it, how could it not be
as bad as touching a little piece of bone? Why do we
say a חצי לוג *chatzi log* even for touching? That's what he
argued. ואינו דין שיהא נזיר מגלח nazir megalei'ach. על מגעו ועל משאו
*Ve'eino din she-ya-nazir megaleach al maga'o v'al masa'o*? אמר לי ר' אליעזר
*Amar li Rabbi Eliezer*. ר' אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer* said back to me,
מה זה עקיבא *Ma zeh Akiva*? What do you want from me,
עקיבא *Akiva*? אין דנים כאן מקל וחומר *Ein danim kan mi-kal vachomer*.
You don't... קל וחומר kal vachomer, *kal vachomer* is not relevant in
these laws, which presumably means these are just arbitrary laws. This is
not the place, עקיבא *Akiva*, for all of your brilliant logic. These
are just arbitrary laws. וכשבאתי והרציתי דברי לפני ר' יהושע *Uchshebati v'hirtzeiti
devarai lifnei Rabbi Yehoshua*. ר' עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* did not like that
response and did not feel it addressed enough his concerns, so he
went to his other teacher, ר' יהושע *Rabbi Yehoshua*. אמר לי יפה
אמרת *Amar li: Yafeh amarta*. Look, it was a good argument. אלא
כך אמרו הלכה halakha? *Ela kach amru halacha*. But nevertheless, that's the
tradition. So there's not much of a difference between them, except here's
the difference, every דוב *Dov* will appreciate this as an educator: he
validated it. He said, you know what? That's a good point, you
make a very good argument. And he also explained why it's not
relevant. Because here it's just a הלכה למשה מסיני halakha le-Moshe mi-Sinai
*Halacha l'Moshe mi-Sinai*. It's a good argument, it was validated, he told
him why nevertheless it didn't matter, as opposed to ר' אליעזר *Rabbi
Eliezer* that just says, ר' עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva*, there's no place for
this here, like just rejected it. Now another interesting thing
on is, and this is sort of the particularly around the difference
between ר' אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer* and ר' עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva*, is what
ר' עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* sort of brought to תורה שבעל פה Torah
she-bi-al peh *Torah she-ba'al peh*, it's not like he was the only
one, it's also in like what הלל *Hillel* brought to it like
many generations before, but was much more the idea of using logic
and human creativity and not seeing it as just about passing down
traditions. And that in particular in a number of stories is highlighted,
well, to some degree it starts with... So well because going back
to there's a whole famous story about could you bring a קרבן
korban פסח when ערב פסח Erev Pesach fell out on שבת? Shabbat?
Right? Would it be דוחה doche שבת? Shabbat? And it basically says
that nobody knew the הלכה, halakha nobody remembered what the הלכה halakha
is, and then somebody said, oh wait, there's some sage named הלל
הבבלי Hillel HaBavli who he studied under שמעיה ואבטליון Shemaya v'Avtalyon and
he's here. So then הלל הבבלי Hillel HaBavli came and he made
all these קל וחומרים kal vachomers whatever to say that it's דוחה
doche שבת. Shabbat. And it says he spent the whole day trying
to convince them and they wouldn't and they didn't accept it until
he said, כך מקובלני משמעיה ואבטליון. Kach mikublani miShemaya v'Avtalyon. Oh, you
have a tradition! Okay, fine. So anyway, but what that's setting up
is right is about how much is תורה שבעל פה torah sheba'al
peh, about a tradition and how much is it about actually using
your reasoning and approaching the issue through logic and through reasoning. So
the same is true that similar type of a dynamic exists with
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. And there's a
lot of interesting stories around that. That רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer is
just this is my tradition. רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer never said anything
he didn't hear מרבו. merabbo. Okay? And רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva is
very much using his logic. So it's interesting that רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer was more dismissive of רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. Like he just
said, עקיבא, don't bother me with your סברות, sevaras, okay? The same
point, רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua said the same point, right? But it's
interesting that רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer was more dismissive because fundamentally רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer was all about tradition and רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
was like all about derivation and creativity and human intellect and so
on. Okay, so anyway, so that's the interesting like subtext that's going
on here. Let's take a look at the גמרא, Gemara, yeah.
When there was discussion whether it should be a רביעית revi'is or
a חצי לוג for the blood earlier, was it רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva who was suggesting a רביעית?
revi'is Exactly, exactly, yes. It came up before a quarter לוג and
that was רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and that was based on this.
Yes. איבעיא להו. Iba'ya lehu. So they raise the following question, says
גמרא. Gemara. עצם כשעורה הלכה ורביעית דם קל וחומר ואין דנים קל
וחומר מהלכה. Etzem k'se'orah halakha v'revi'is dam kal vachomer v'ein danim kal
vachomer me-halakha. Now what is when he says this is a הלכה,
halakha. what the גמרא Gemara really wants to know is, what's a
הלכה? halacha What is the הלכה למשה מסיני halakha le-Moshe mi-Sinai. here?
Is it the הלכה halacha that even a tiny little bit of
bone is enough for a נזיר nazir to be מגולח? megalei'ach? Why
is that a חידוש? chiddush? Well, that could be a חידוש chiddush
because as תוספות Tosafos says, what does the פסוק pasuk say by
a נזיר? nazir By a נזיר Nazir it says, על כל נפשות
מת לא יבוא. al kol nafshos meis lo yavo. So תוספות Tosafos
says if you actually ask פשט pshat of the פסוקים psukim might
say only if it's טומאת אוהל tumas ohel or minimally only if
he became טמא tamei through something that has the power to create
טומאת אוהל. tumas ohel. It says לא יבוא. lo yavo. So maybe
there's a חידוש chiddush in the idea that he's טמא tamei even
with a little chip of bone which doesn't have the power of
טומאת אוהל. tumas ohel. So that's one thing which could be a
הלכה למשה מסיני. halakha le-Moshe mi-Sinai. We didn't think about that, right?
We sort of assumed anything that's טומאת מת tumas meis obviously נזיר
Nazir should be מגולח. megalei'ach. And if there's any exceptions, it's the
exceptions that are הלכה למשה מסיני. halakha le-Moshe mi-Sinai But the גמרא
Gemara is saying, but which one is the הלכה למשה מסיני halakha
le-Moshe mi-Sinai, here? Maybe it's the idea that a נזיר Nazir. could
be מגולח megalei'ach even on a little chip of bone. So what
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua were saying back
to him is, don't bring proofs from the הלכה halacha: that he's
מגולח megalei'ach on the chip of bone because that is an exception.
Okay? You're right, logically you should only be מגולח megalei'ach on something
that's טומאת אוהל, tumas ohel, that has the power of טומאת אוהל.
tumas ohel. But okay, don't bring proofs from the chip of bone.
The chip of bone is an exception. So that's one way of
saying it. איבעיא Iba'ya עצם כשעורה הלכה ורביעית דם קל וחומר ואין
דנים קל וחומר מהלכה. etzem k'se'orah halakha v'revi'is dam kal vachomer v'ein
danim kal vachomer me-halakha. You don't learn it from the chip of
bone but meaning the point is the chip of bone is the
exception. Now in the process chip of bone, what, well, okay, could
be, they could be both but even one presumably is enough to
say you don't make a קל וחומר. kal vachomer או דילמא O
dilma or do you say the other one? רביעית דם הלכה. Revi'is
dam halakha. רביעית דם revi'is dam. is the הלכה. halacha: ועצם כשעורה
קל וחומר. V'etzem k'se'orah kal vachomer. And the עצם כשעורה etzem k'se'orah
is the קל וחומר. kal v'chomer Now it's the same קל וחומר,
kal v'chomer, you're learning from the bone to the רביעית דם. revi'is
dam ואין דנים קל וחומר מהלכה. V'ein danim kal vachomer me-halakha. But
what it means is, maybe the הלכה למשה מסיני, halakha le-Moshe mi-Sinai
the exception is not the bone, but it's the רביעית revi'is of
blood. Why is the רביעית revi'is of blood the exception? What's the
exception about the רביעית revi'is of blood? So the exception about the
רביעית revi'is of blood the way תוספות Tosafos says is that the
פסוקים psukim say what is it? על כל נפשות מת לא יבוא,
Al kol nafshos meis lo yavo, okay? לאביו ולאמו לא יטמא, L'aviv
ul'imo lo yitama, right? This is by the כהן. Now תוספות Tosafos
so על נפשות מת, al nafshos meis, נפש מת nefesh meis is
what we say means blood. Remember what רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva דרשן
darshans from נפשות מת? nafshos meis? Even if the רביעית revi'is blood
comes from two people, it's the plural. But תוספות Tosafos but תוספות
Tosafos says the other way of reading what the plural means is
that you need the minimum amount for two people. So you need
two רביעיות revi'ises which is a חצי לוג. So what he could
be saying back is, you know, the simple sense of the פסוקים
psukim by a כהן is that טומאה's tumah. really only with a
חצי לוג of blood. So the fact that a רביעית revi'is of
blood causes טומאת אוהל, tumas ohel, that's a חידוש. chiddush. So don't
try to use your רביעית blood to make a קל וחומר kal
v'chomer from the bone that if the bone is enough נזיר Nazir
מגולח megalei'ach the רביעית דם revi'is dam should be נזיר Nazir. מגולח,
megalei'ach, because the רביעית דם revi'is dam is a חידוש chiddush that's
a הלכה למשה מסיני halacha l'moshe misinai? that that's enough for טומאה.
tumah Logically you should... Logically you should've needed a half of a
לוג for טומאת אוהל. tumas ohel. Okay, so this is the question,
which is the הלכה למשה מסיני? halacha l'moshe misinai Is it that
even this little bit of bone is enough for נזיר nazir מגלח,
megalei'ach that's the חידוש, chiddush, cause the פסוקים pesukim emphasize טומאת אוהל
tumas ohel and you can't learn anything from the הלכה halacha of
this bone, or is it that the רביעית that even a רביעית
of it causes טומאת אוהל, tumas ohel, that is a הלכה למשה
מסיני halacha l'moshe misinai, and you can't use that to argue that
therefore it should be enough for נזיר nazir מגלח. megalei'ach So let's
just read the answer, so which is it? תא שמע, ta shema,
come and hear, עצם כשעורה הלכה, etzem k'se'ora halacha, so we have
a ברייתא beraisa that says it explicitly. The rule that the little
bit of bone causes נזיר nazir. to be מגלח, m'galei'ach, that's the
הלכה למשה מסיני, halacha l'moshe misinai ורביעית דם קל וחומר, v'revi'is dam
kal v'chomer, and רביעית דם is just that's you don't need הלכה
למשה מסיני halacha l'moshe misinai, for the רביעית of blood, and we
should be able to make, and you're trying to use a קל
וחומר kal v'chomer from the fact that נזיר nazir, is מגלח m'galei'ach
on the רביעית blood to say he should be, I'm sorry, that
the fact that נזיר nazir, is מגלח megaleiach, on a bone, to
say he should be מגלח megaleiach on a רביעית of blood, אין
דנים קל וחומר להלכה. ein danim kal v'chomer l'halacha. You can't make
a קל וחומר, you can't start from a case that itself is
labeled as an exception, as a חידוש, chiddush, as הלכה למשה מסיני,
halacha l'moshe misinai the bone, and try to derive something from it.
Okay, that's just sort of sui generis, sui genre, whatever it's called.
That's the that's the הלכה למשה מסיני halacha l'moshe misinai is true
about the bone, it doesn't and it's not meant to be to
indicate any larger rule or any larger principle that then you can
then infer from it. Jonathan, you have a question? Yes, so when
we say that הלכה למשה מסיני halacha l'moshe misinai? is an exception,
what's the underpinning of the thought that we can't use a הלכה
halachah, to derive a קל וחומר from our הלכה למשה מסיני? halacha
l'moshe misinais, It just seems just the opposite, that's a fundamental. Yeah,
I mean it's a good point, but I think that the, I
mean, somehow that's the way, sometimes it's an exception, sometimes it's like
an independent rule, like you know there's some הלכה למשה מסיני, halacha
l'moshe misinai you know, about, you know, about like I don't know,
like ערבות aravos in the בית המקדש beis hamikdash over over סוכות,
sukkos, right? That wasn't an exception, that was just its own thing.
But yeah, somehow generally, it's a good question, but you know, somehow,
going back to this point I made about like human derivation as
opposed to tradition, somehow the whole engagement is like, you know, we
using the י"ג מדות yud gimmel middos or hermeneutic principles to engage
the פסוקים pesukim of the תורה, torah, to work with a text.
And you start with a text and then you use these logical
principles and you derive law, and that's sort of the whole arena
of, you know, rational sort of logical engagement, whereas הלכה למשה מסיני
halacha l'moshe misinai the whole point is, this is a tradition that
was passed down. So the fact that it was a tradition sort
of makes it all about just, you know, the received law and
not about something that's part of a larger intellectual discourse like that,
you know. But you're right, you could still say, okay, it's a
tradition, let's try to figure out what the tradition is telling us.
So there's no like a priori reason why that's true, but that's
that's the assumption, you know, that if you want to engage your
intellect, that's the that's the role of תורה שבעל פה, torah sheba'al
peh that's the role of engaging the text, you know. הלכה למשה
מסיני halacha l'moshe misinai is just like straight tradition. Yeah, so is
this accurate, up until now I would have said fundamentally there are
two sources of authority for הלכה: halachah. דרשה drasha on a פסוק
pasuk and סברא. s'vara. Yeah. But now it sounds like really that's
not accurate. What we're saying is there are two foundations for הלכה:
halacha. הלכה למשה מסיני halacha l'moshe misinai which is a standalone, and
then פסוקים, pesukim, you always need a פסוק pasuk to then derive
another הלכה halacha from a קל וחומר and not need a second
פסוק pasuk as it were, like like סברא s'vara and פסוקים, pesukim,
דרשן פסוקים darshan pesukim are more linked. Well, yeah, I mean that
was a point that we've made before, that came up with the
מדרש הלכה midrash halacha we called before, like that that's always true.
You know, you there's some things you can just figure out totally
on your own, למה לי קרא סברא הוא, lama li kra s'vara
hu, but fundamentally the source of authority from the פסוקים pesukim is
also through the lens of תורה Torah שבעל פה and מדרש הלכה
midrash halacha which is also the use of סברא, s'vara, absolutely. Yeah,
it's only הלכה למשה מסיני halacha l'moshe misinai. to then build a
סברא s'vara on that. Exactly, and that's always going to be according
to this a פסוק. pasuk. Well, I don't know I know always
a פסוק, pasuk, I mean there's some things maybe you could just
like whatever self-evident type of סברא s'vara things. But but yeah, often
it starts with knowing what the basic rules of the game are.
Yeah, the stuff that is just straight tradition and not סברא s'vara
is the הלכה למשה מסיני. halachah l'moshe m'sinai, Right. Okay, let's go
on now to הדרן עלך כהן גדול, hadran alach kohein gadol, we're
finally done with that, with all the various טומאת מן המת. tumas
min ha-meis. And now we are get sort of into a completely
different topic, but we touch on but it's something that we saw
just a day ago and that touches on things that we've discussed
that we've it touches on the realities of the implications of טומאת
מת tumas meis without getting into the very concrete details. So let's
take a look. שני נזירים, shnei nezirim, there are two נזירים, nezirim,
שאמר להן אחד, she'amar lahen echad, one person says to the two
of them, ראיתי אחד מכם שנטמא, ra'isi echad mikem she-nitma, you know
I saw one of you become טמא, tamei, walk into a graveyard,
you didn't realize it was a graveyard, ואיני יודע איזה מכם, v'eini
yodeia eizeh mikem, but I don't remember which one of you it
was, or at the time I didn't know which one of you
it was. So now you have two נזירים, nezirim, each one is
ספק נזיר טמא. safek nazir tamei. So what do they do? So
if you're ספק נזיר טמא... safek nazir tamei... Let's just say if
you're one ספק נזיר טמא, safek nazir tamei, you'd have to go
through the process of bringing the קרבן טומאה korban tumah and then
go through טהרה, taharah, but one minute, how can you bring the
קרבן טומאה? korban tumah? There's two problems. Number one, you can't bring
the קרבן korban if you're not חייב chayav in it. Good question.
Number two is that you can't shave if you're not a נזיר
טמא, nazir tamei, right? So to wait, so in order to shave,
this is like we said before, you'd have to wait 30 days
or till the end of let's assume you did a minimum נזירות.
nezirut Okay, so now you could be shaving as a נזיר טהור
nazir tahor or as a נזיר טמא, nazir tamei, it's okay to
shave. As far as the קרבן korban is concerned, one of the
קרבנות korbanot is an עולה, olah, so you would just bring the
עולה olah and you would stipulate and you would say, if this
is an, if I'm חייב chayav as a נזיר טמא, nazir tamei,
this is my עולה olah of obligation, if it's not then it's
a נדבה, nedavah, it's a free will, and assuming one sacrifice is
enough to change your state, which we're assuming, that would therefore be
good. Then you'd wait another 30 days because you might be a
נזיר טהור, nazir tahor, right? And then you would go ahead and
bring and shave again. Right, so if you were a נזיר טמא
nazir tamei now you need to wait, if you were a נזיר
טהור nazir tahor you're done, right? But if you were a נזיר
טמא nazir tamei you need to wait another 30 days now to
finish your normal נזירות nezirus and then again you bring a קרבן
korban, and you stipulate and now you can shave. Do you bring
a חטאת chatat each time? No. So the חטאת, chatat, so here's,
the חטאת chatat you can't bring בספק. b'safek. You can't bring any
for the קרבנות טומאה korbanot tumah you can only bring, well here's
a thing, you actually for the קרבן טומאה korban tumah you can
bring the חטאת chatat is a bird and there's actually a הלכה,
halacha another הלכה halacha למשה מסיני, whatever anyway, that you can bring
a חטאת העוף chatat ha'of על הספק. al ha-safek. So when you,
for the first set when you were ספק נזיר טמא, safek nazir
tamei, you brought an עולה olah for the בתנאי b'tnai and חטאת
העוף chatat ha'of בספק. b'safek. Okay, and you also had to bring
an עולה olah as a נזיר טהור nazir tahor because if you
weren't a נזיר טמא nazir tamei and you were about to shave,
you needed to end your נזירות טהרה, nezirut taharah, so you would
have to bring a, right, two עולות? olot? In that case at
the end of the first. So here you are, right here you
are, you're ספק טמא, safek tamei, okay? Anyway, you're ספק טמא, safek
tamei, right? So what do you do? But you might also be
טהור. tahor. So from the Torah perspective you can't shave now, if
you were טמא tamei you could, you have to wait 30 days.
Okay, from the טמא tamei you could do it right now, but
you don't have that choice, you have to do both. Now you're
going to shave. If you're going to shave, in order to allow
you to shave if you're a נזיר טהור, nazir tahor, you'd have
to bring at least one קרבן, korban, okay? So that would be
an עולה בתנאי. olah b'tnai. If you're a טמא tamei in order
to allow you to shave, you also have to bring one קרבן,
korban so you would bring an עולה בתנאי olah b'tnai and luckily
because the חטאת chatat here is a חטאת העוף, chatat ha'of, you're
allowed to bring a חטאת העוף chatat ha'of מספק mi-safek as well,
that's a special הלכה. halacha What? And there's an אשם? asham? Yeah,
but that you can't bring מספק mi-safek and you can't bring בתנאי.
b'tnai. So this is the only, these are the things that you're
allowed to bring and assuming that one קרבן korban, is enough, then
that allows you to now shave. You're either shaving because you ended
your נזירות טהרה nezirut taharah and that you brought one קרבן, korban
or you're shaving because you ended your נזירות טומאה nezirut tumah and
you brought the קרבנות. korbanot. Wait, can you explain your model? Because
I had been under the impression that when you bring something or
you do something בתנאי, b'tnai, you only do one act and the
תנאי tnai directs its name. Oh, so the תנאי tnai normally means,
good point, the תנאי tnai normally means either this is the קרבן
korban. I'm חייב chayav for or it's a נדבה. nedavah. Now what
you're saying is why don't you say this is either the קרבן
טהרה korban taharah or the קרבן טומאה? korban tumah? Point is they're
different animals, okay? They're different, so you can't make the תנאי, tnai,
you can't say this עולה olah either works for טהרה taharah or
for טומאה tumah because the עולות olot are different עולות. olot. So
then you're bringing both and what's the תנאי tnai and you're doing
both and then right, I mean if you are טמא tamei you're
bringing a טהור tahor when you shouldn't, which is the whole thing
we were trying to avoid in the first place. Yeah but this
is, if you are טמא, tamei, then this counted as your עולה
olah for טומאה tumah and this counted as your חטאת, chatat, and
this was just an עולת נדבה. olat nedavah. The תנאי tnai is
עולת נדבה. olat nedavah. Okay? And if you were טהור, tahor, this
was your עולה olah of obligation and this was an עולת נדבה
olat nedavah and this was an allowance that you could bring a
חטאת מספק. chatat mi-safek. Okay, the תנאי tnai is either חיוב chiyuv
or נדבה. nedavah. Yeah. Can you just, what does he bring at
the end of the second 30 days? Okay, so I'm getting there.
Okay, now that's the first 30 days. Now, assuming you are טהור,
tahor, you're done. But you might have been טמא. tamei. So you
have to wait another 30 days, okay? And at the end of
the 30 days, assuming you were טמא, tamei, you'd have to, you're
going to be מגלח, okay? Which you're totally allowed to do now
because either way you're good. Okay, but you can only be מגלח
after bringing a קרבן. korban Now what קרבן korban can you bring?
Well, you might have already brought your obligatory, you might be done.
So you can't just say let me just bring all the קרבנות
korbanot that another, a נזיר nazir, brings, because I might have been
done being a נזיר nazir back here. So you're only allowed to
bring one קרבן korban which is your, which is an עולה, olah,
and you bring it בתנאי. b'tnai. Okay, and this should be just
so if. And the תנאי t'nai is if I was already done
this is a נדבה. nedavah. Right? If I wasn't done then this
is my עולה olah of the end of נזירות nezirut. of טהרה.
tahara. Okay? So there's no אשם asham on the whole thing. So
you're never going to be able to bring an אשם. asham. Now
what I'd like to know although I didn't see תוספות Tosafot address
it is well you're never going to bring an אשם asham for
the טמא tamei because you might not ever have been טמא. tamei.
What I'd like to know is at this stage can you bring
the חטאת, chatat, can you bring your חטאת chatat thirty days later?
Because you definitely were a נזיר טהור. nazir tahor. Right? Now you
couldn't bring it here but at the end of sixty days you
are definitely done. So even if you brought your עולה olah here
and you were done here could I postpone my חטאת chatat for
נזיר טהור nazir tahor for thirty days? That I don't know, okay.
If so then I would say you bring the עולה olah בתנאי
bitnai and you bring the rest of your קרבנות korbanot here because
by this day you're definitely חייב chayav all your קרבנות korbanot of
נזירות. nezirus That I don't know the answer to that. But this
is what a normal person would say, a normal situation that he
has a ספק. safek. Now two people have a ספק. safek. One
of them is טמא tamei one of them is not. How are
they going to deal with it? Yes. So we learned that earlier
in an earlier פרק, perek, it was a debate, but anyway that
was that was the accepted הלכה. If it's not enough then you're
really really stuck. I don't know what you'd do. Okay. So let's
see what happens. Yeah. How many days he would have to have
a שליח shaliach bring for him? Because the ספק טמא safek tamei
can't go to the עזרה. azarah. Yeah but right but he would
be טהור tahor from טומאת מת tumat meis he would go with
the ashes of שלישי ושביעי shlishi v'shvi'i be טהור. tahor. You'd only
be- and it wouldn't even be a מחוסר כפורים mechusar kipurim because
the קרבן korban is to start the נזירות neziros not to end
the- end the טומאה. tumah So no he'd be able to come
to the בית המקדש. beis hamikdash. Okay so it says like this:
ואיני יודע איזה מכם v'eini yodeia eizeh mikem מגלחין ומביאין קרבן טומאה
megalchin umvei'in korban tumah okay וקרבן טהרה. v'korban tahara. Okay. So they're
going to wind up between them bringing a קרבן טומאה korban tumah
and קרבן טהרה. korban tahara. ואומר v'omer but here's what you benefit
from is that you don't have to double up because now if
you've got this other guy here that is in the same situation
as you are, okay, he's in the same situation as you are
when you get here, okay, basically one of you is obligated in
the טומאה קרבנות tumah korbanot and one of you is obligated in
the טהרה קרבן. tahara korban. So each person doesn't have to bring
both sets. You can just bring this collection here and stipulate and
say the set I have to bring is for me and the
set you have to bring is for you. Is that clear? You're
going to treat the two people as if they're one person making
the תנאי. t'nai. Well yeah I mean essentially. תוספות Tosafot says you
don't even have to say the תנאי t'nai basically it's like- in
a certain way well we'll see like okay let's read it. Okay.
ואומר אם אני הוא הטמא קרבן טומאה שלי וקרבן טהרה שלך v'omer
im ani hu hatamei korban tumah sheli v'korban tahara shelcha ואם אני
הוא הטהור קרבן טהרה שלי וקרבן טומאה שלך. v'im ani hu hatahor
korban tahara sheli v'korban tumah shelcha. So basically actually if there's two
people you don't need the תנאי t'nai because then at this stage
after thirty days one of them is definitely obligated a קרבן טומאה
korban tumah and one is definitely obligated a קרבן טהרה. korban tahara.
So you don't have to make any- so you can bring the
full amount okay not just an עולה. olah. You have a full
קרבן טומאה korban tumah here, right, which is חטאת, chatat, עולה, olah,
אשם, asham, etc. Okay you have a full קרבן טומאה korban tumah
and you have a full קרבן טהרה. korban tahara. Okay you don't
have to do only the עולה. olah. You have the עולה olah
and the חטאת chatat because definitely one person has to bring one
and the other is the other. You don't have to stipulate it'll
be a נדבה. nedavah. The only stipulation you have to say is
the טהרה tahara one is going for the טהור tahor guy and
the טומאה tumah one is going for the טמא tamei guy. But
you're able to bring both full sets and you just have to
say the sets are going to the one of the- to the
one of the two of them that is obligated. Okay. וסופרים שלושים
יום v'sofren shloshim yom and then at the end of thirty days
again you don't need a תנאי t'nai because at the end of
thirty days definitely one of them is חייב chayav now the one
who was טמא tamei is חייב chayav now a full, right, a
קרבן טהרה, korban tahara, full קרבן טהרה. korban tahara. You just don't
know which one. So here's what you say at the end of
the second thirty days. ואומר אם אני הוא הטמא v'omer im ani
hu hatamei if I was the one that was טמא tamei then
קרבן טומאה שלי korban tumah sheli then the קרבן טומאה korban tumah
I brought thirty days ago that was mine and קרבן טהרה שלך
v'korban tahara shelcha and the טהרה tahara was yours that's thirty days
ago. וזה v'zeh now thirty days later this one קרבן טהרתי korban
taharati this is for me being טהור tahor because I was the
one who was טמא. tamei. ואם אני הוא הטהור v'im ani hu
hatahor if I was the one who was טהור tahor קרבן טהרה
שלי וקרבן טומאה שלך korban tahara sheli v'korban tumah shelcha thirty days
ago my קרבן korban was the one of טהור tahor and yours
was טומאה. וזה v'zeh this is קרבן טהרתך. korban taharatcha. So in
the end instead of having to do all these תנאים tna'im and
only bringing a certain minimum amount of קרבנות korbanot only the עולות
olos you get to bring the whole thing and just say it
goes to the person. who needs it. Okay. So if there's going
to be a ספק טמא, safek tamei, best is to do it
together with another person. אמן. Amen. All right. So תביא משנים מן
האחד. Tavi mishnayim min ha'echad. Yes. Can a... can a קרבן korban...
be brought not knowing exactly who it's... Yeah. Yeah. What about סמיכה?
smicha? All right, so you would... I mean סמיכה smicha isn't מעכב,
me'akev, but you know, but the basic הלכה is that if you,
you know, if you... you can שחט shacht the קרבן... korban, I
mean the כהנים Kohanim would not have to keep track like before
they got a קרבן, korban, you know, read the little tag on
the קרבן, korban oh, this is for Charlie Hall. And you know,
they would just שחט shacht it for whoever's קרבן korban it was.
And תוספות Tosfos sort of says that. תוספות Tosfos says you don't
even need to say anything or make a תנאי. tnai. I mean,
there's an interesting question about ownership and who are you מקדיש makdish
it for, okay, but basically the כהנים will just bring it for
whoever's קרבן korban. it is, right? All right, so let's take a
look at the גמרא. Gemara. If I lived at the time of
the מקדש, Mikdash, I'd want to be a veterinarian. All right. תני,
Tani, שני נזירים. shne nezirim. Our משנה mishna says two נזירים... nezirim...
שאמר להם ראיתי אחד מכם שנטמא ואיני יודע איזה מכם. sh'amar lahem
re'isi echad mikem she-nitma ve'eini yode'a eizeh mikem. Okay, and I don't
know which one. Now the גמרא Gemara has a question that you
probably wouldn't have expected. ואמאי, Ve'amai, why are they ספק טמא? safek
tamei? כל ספק טומאה ברשות היחיד מהיכא ילפינן לה, Kol safek tumah
birshut hayachid meheicha yalpinan lah, so the idea that a ספק טמא,
safek tamei, presumably what we're saying is since you're ספק טמא, safek
tamei, we treat you as you might be טמא, tamei, but one
minute. The idea, where did this take place? In a private or
in a... domain or in a public domain? It's not the same
definition as in שבת, Shabbos, but it means basically in a place
of relative seclusion or in a public place. Why does that matter?
Because we have a principle that we learn from סוטה, Sotah, the
סוטה Sotah actually next מסכת maseches coming up, that the woman who
is suspected of committing adultery, it says ונסתרה ונטמאה, venistara vehitma, she
went into seclusion in the hiding and she perhaps became טמא, tamei,
but it doesn't say she perhaps, it says she did become טמא,
tamei, which means, and that's basically the story of a סוטה, Sotah,
that we... that we assume that she is טמא, tamei, that she
committed adultery, that's what... I mean in that context, that's what טומאה
means, that she committed adultery until she goes through the process of
the... of the סוטה Sotah process. So her doubtful status, and it
was in private and it was all this circumstantial evidence, basically we
have this presumption until that gets cleared up. That becomes interest... although
טומאה there means something very different, that becomes a model for laws
of more ritual טומאה וטהרה. tumah v'tahara. That if there's a doubt
whether something became טמא tamei or not, if it was in ברשות
היחיד birshut hayachid like ונסתרה, venistara, in a private place, we assume
it's טמא, tamei, and if it was in a public place, we
assume that it is טהור. tahor. ספק טומאה ברשות היחיד ספיקו טמא
ספק טומאה ברשות הרבים ספיקו טהור, Safek tumah birshut hayachid sfeko tamei,
safek tumah birshut harabim sfeko tahor, even דאורייתא. d'oraisa. We assume that
that's a דאורייתא d'oraisa principle. Again, and making this big conceptual jump
from the use of the word טומאה by סוטה Sotah to other
cases. And even in סוטה, Sotah, there was like circumstantial evidence. Here
there's no circumstantial evidence. It's just 'I don't know did I touch
it or not touch it?' Oh, so it's רשות היחיד, reshus hayachid,
you're טמא. tamei. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says since the משנה
Mishnah is assuming that they're טמא, tamei, the גמרא Gemara says so
why, it must have been a רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid. But one
minute. It couldn't have been a רשות היחיד. reshus hayachid. The גמרא
Gemara says ואמאי כל ספק טומאה ברשות היחיד מהיכא ילפינן לה מסוטה.
ve'amai kol safek tumah birshut hayachid meheicha yalpinan lah mi-Sotah. מה סוטה
בו וניבעל, Mah Sotah bo venival, in the case of the סוטה
Sotah who are the only people in the room? The... the man
and the woman. אף כל ספק טומאה ברשות היחיד, af kol safek
tumah birshut hayachid, anytime we say that it's a ספק טומאה safek
tumah when it comes in a private setting, that it's ספק טמא,
safek tamei, כגון דאיכא בי תרי, k'gon de'ika bei terei, only if
there are two people. אבל הכא שני נזירים והאי, Aval hacha, shne
nezirim vehai, it's the two נזירים nezirim and this guy who is
with them, דקאי גבייהו, de'kai gabei'hon, that is with them, הא תלתא,
ha telasa, that's three people. So הוי ליה ספק טומאה ברשות הרבים,
havei lei safek tumah birshut harabim, so three people already makes it
public. And once it's public, ספיקו טהור, sfeko tahor, they should just
both be considered טהור. tahor. Now again, even though it's not possible
for both of them to be טהור, tahor, we nevertheless say that
each one of you comes with your question, am I... am I
נזיר nazir or not, and we say well it occurred in the
רשות הרבים, reshus harabim, uh you're not. Okay, so you're both sort
of ספק טהור. safek tahor. Now this is interesting because it gets
to these questions of can you apply these principles when in the
totality they both can't be true, that they both can't be טהור.
tahor. The flip side of that is, but the גמרא Gemara here
assumes they can. There's a classic case of two people that went
on two paths and there's definitely a grave buried under under a
path. So if each one goes separately to the רבי Rabbi to
say what's my status, the רבי Rabbi will say you're טהור, tahor,
ספק טומאה ברשות הרבים, safek tumah birshut harabim, assuming the path is
in public. What if they both show up to the רבי at
the same time? Okay, and it's possible that even there he says
you're both טהור. tahor. It's possible the only case that he has
to say that they're ספק טמא safek tamei is if one guy
comes and says 'Me and my friend went on these parallel paths,'
so it's ultimately like one question, then maybe you'd be forced to
say that they're טמא. tamei. Here the גמרא Gemara assumes that if
it's רשות הרבים, reshus harabim, even though one of them is טמא,
tamei, we would rule both of them are טהור. tahor. But תוספות
Tosfos basically asks the flip. תוספות Tosfos says one minute, but the
principle that ספק טומאה ברשות היחיד safek tumah birshut hayachid is טמא,
tamei, which the גמרא Gemara would like to apply here, the הלכה
there is not ספק טמא, safek tamei, the הלכה there is we
treat it as if it's ודאי טמא, vadai tamei, I mean we
sort of acknowledge that we don't know the facts, but nevertheless the
הלכה is that we treat it as ודאי טמא vadai tamei until.
Other facts indicate otherwise, that's like the story of the סוטה, sotah,
okay? So תוספות Tosafot says, so why isn't this משנה Mishnah, having
everybody bringing a קרבן מספק? korban misafek? If it really was a
רשות היחיד, reshut hayachid, they would have to be considered ודאי טמא,
vadai tamei, not ספק טמא. safek tamei. That would be the way
the rules would apply. So תוספות Tosafot says that... and that's an
interesting question... is these rules of ספק טומאה ברשות היחיד טמא safek
tumah bireshut hayachid tamei that you maintain the element of ספק safek
when you rule that the person is טמא. tamei. So תוספות Tosafot
says normally we would say they were ודאי טמא, vadai tamei, but
since it's not possible, so here he says the thing in the
reverse of them both being טהור, tahor, it's not possible for both
of them to be ודאי טמא, vadai tamei, then we would say
that we treat it as ספק טומאה. safek tumah. So normally if
only one of them came, one נזיר nazir came and said I
was in a רשות היחיד, reshut hayachid, I might have touched this
dead body, I don't know if I did or whatever, then we
say oh, ספק טמא, safek tamei, you're considered ודאי טמא vadai tamei
and go ahead and you know ודאי vadai bring a קרבן. But
in this case where both of them are it, we can't say
they're both ודאי טמא, vadai tamei, that's not true, so we treat
it as a ספק טומאה. safek tumah. So that's interesting, right, about
that? But I will, I do want to say remember we started
this with only one person, remember the last few days we've been
dealing with a case of a נזיר who's a ספק טמא safek
tamei and we're going to come up with that again how he
keeps sixty days or a hundred and twenty days or four years.
So it is possible to be a ספק טמא safek tamei with
a נזיר. So it does not seem that it's a simple, maybe
it's not simple, it does not seem that it's clear what תוספות
Tosafot says that when we say ספק, safek, it's ספק טמא safek
tamei becomes ודאי טמא, vadai tamei, because all that we're dealing with
whether it's one נזיר or two נזירים, nezirim, we're going to be
dealing with a lot of cases of ספק טמא safek tamei remaining
as a ספק. safek. Okay? So that is an interesting question whether
these rules end in a ספק safek or whether ספק טמא safek
tamei or end in a ודאי טמא. vadai tamei. Yes, Zenda question.
And it's not clear where the possible טמא, tamei, like here it's
not clear to me that he's like looking... you just became possibly
טמא. tamei. It's like I saw you some time ago and it's
not clear whether that time ago... Right, but that time ago if
everybody was in the same space and he saw them in... so
he assumes it's the same, you assume it's the same two guys
and they were... well when did you see, when did you see
this happen? A week ago. What was happening? Well we were all
at this party and somebody dropped dead, I don't know, whatever. And
one of them touched him, I didn't see which one of them
touched him. Well then there were three of you there, right? So
whatever it happened, there were three of them there. That's the... but
it's interesting, you don't consider the... well, yes. But it could have
just been one and he's like you look similar and I'm not
sure which of you it was. So that's... meaning maybe I saw
different events or something like that with each of them, right? So
could be. But so the גמרא Gemara will give an answer like
that, yes. Does this have to be a witness to סוטה sotah
as well? What? A witness that she went into seclusion but not
that she actually committed the act. Okay, because they're making a distinction
here between the two, just two in סוטה sotah and three here
because the witness... Who was? Yes, but in the סוטה sotah there
was not the third person wasn't with them in the room. Here,
right, that the space they were in was only the two of
them. So that's the גמרא's Gemara question. So it's not a ספק
טומאה ברשות היחיד, safek tumah bireshut hayachid, it's a רשות הרבים reshut
harabim because כל ספק טומאה ברשות הרבים ספקו טהור. kol safek tumah
bireshut harabim sefeko tahor. אמר רבה בר בר חנה באומר ראיתי טומאה
שנזרקה ביניכם. Amar Rabbah bar bar Chana be'omer ra'isi tumah shenizreka beineichem.
Basically I was standing at a distance and I just saw the
two of you and I maybe and I couldn't make out like
who was who, basically like Dena was saying, or and or I
saw a טומאה that sort of I don't know שנזרקה ביניכם. shenizreka
beineichem. I don't know somebody threw a piece of a dead body.
I mean it's just a little gross or graphic. But anyway but
the point is I wasn't standing there with you. I saw the
two of you at a distance and therefore the space you were
in was a רשות היחיד. reshut hayachid. Okay. אמר רב אשי דיקא
נמי Amar Rav Ashi diyka nami that also inferred from the language
דתני ואיני יודע איזה מכם. detani ve'eini yodeia eize mikem. שמע מינה.
Shema mina. So I don't know, and the גמרא Gemara understands that
somehow this suggests it's not like I forgot which one of you,
I can't recognize which one of you. איני יודע Eini yodeia means
somehow like I never knew which one of you was the one.
So that works better with the scenario that you saw at a
distance and you couldn't tell which one of them actually touched, okay?
So that's how it was רשות היחיד. reshut hayachid. So again we
said it's a רשות היחיד reshut hayachid but we're saying assuming that
ספק טומאה ברשות היחיד safek tumah bireshut hayachid is ספק טמא safek
tamei not ודאי טמא. vadai tamei. Everybody get that point that we're
retaining the ספק? safek? So that does seem to be an assumption
we're making throughout that it's possible to have a ספק טומאה safek
tumah and not a... and not a ודאי טומאה, vadai tumah, okay,
even though it's a רשות היחיד. reshut hayachid. Alright so now the
גמרא Gemara says like this, מגלחין ומביאין, megalchin umevi'in, so they shave
and they bring and they make the stipulation. ואמאי, Ve'amai, why is
that? דילמא לאו טמאים אינון וקעביד הקפה. Dilma lav tme'im inun veka'avid
hakafa. Maybe one... I mean one of them isn't טמא tamei and
he is basically doing the איסור issur of cutting his hair. So
you got out with this whole nice scenario that nobody is doing
the איסור issur of cutting your hair as a נזיר. Okay but
everybody is cutting their hair twice, right? What happens at this stage?
Everybody cuts their hair, yes? At stage after the first thirty days.
After the second thirty days they both cut their hair, right? Because
nobody knows which was טמא, tamei, which was טהור. tahor. But says
one minute, the guy who was טהור... tahor... four, he cut his
hair an extra time. And since he's cutting all the hair of
his head, so how's he allowed to do that? Forget that he's
not a נזיר anymore, right? You're not allowed to cut off your
sideburns. How are you allowed to do that? Now it's not clear
what the alternative is, okay, but here's an interesting thing. Even if
a נזיר isn't מגלח, his נזירות neziros is over. You might remember
that, right? That the גילוח giluach is not מעכב. me'akev. So what
the גמרא Gemara seems to be suggesting is, why don't we just
say that each of them only shaves once? So if he was
a נזיר טהור, nazir tahor, you only had everybody shaves once here.
If you were a נזיר טהור, nazir tahor, you're done. If you
were a נזיר טמא, nazir tamei, you shaved once. When you get
here, if you were the guy who was טמא, tamei, fine. Now
you're טהור, tahor, your נזירות neziros. is over, you didn't do the
shaving you were supposed to do at the end of your נזירות.
neziros, Okay, big deal, it's not מעכב. me'akev. Why do we say
that they shave both times, right, so that they get in the
necessary מצוה mitzvah of being מגלח as a נזיר טהור? nazir tahor?
What about the עבירה, aveira, the one of them doesn't need to
be doing that and there's an איסור issur to shave your head?
Okay, so what about that? דמאן אינון? deman inun? If you're not
the one who is טמא, tamei, אי קעבר הקפה, i ka-avar hakafah,
you're doing a הקפה, hakafah,
so why should you be allowed to shave a second time? So
אמר שמואל באשה וקטן, Amar Shmuel be'ishah ve'katan talking about a woman
or a minor who is the נזיר. Now of course why we
have cases of a minor being a נזיר, let's not worry about
the minor, minors aren't obligated in מצות, mitzvos, so doing the הקפה
hakafah is not so bad.
But the more interesting answer, I mean there's חינוך chinuch but whatever,
the more interesting answer is אשה, ishah, okay, which is because and
basically what this is getting us to is that a woman is
not prohibited to shave her beard because women usually don't have beards.
And because there's an assumption that anybody who's in the category of
the איסור issur shaving the beard is in the category of shaving
the sideburns. And if you're not in the איסור issur of shaving
the beard, you're not in the איסור issur of shaving the sideburns.
So since women therefore are excluded from the איסור issur of shaving
the sideburns, so if the woman was the נזירה, nezirah, these are
two women instead of two men, of course one would have imagined
the משנה Mishnah would have mentioned it, but anyway, there's no problem
for them shaving twice, shaving their head twice. Okay, so that's שמואל's
Shmuel answer. So the גמרא Gemara says, ונוקמה בגדול, venokmah begadol, I
don't understand, the גמרא Gemara says there was another answer available to
you. You could have said it was an adult male, not a
woman, והקפת כל הראש לא שמה הקפה, vehakafat kol harosh lo shemah
hakafah, and maybe when you shave all the hair of your head,
you're not transgressing the prohibition of shaving the sideburns. Because what the
תורה Torah says by the sideburns is לא תקיפו, lo takifu, right?
And תקיפו, takifu, להקיף leha'kif is like to make a circle. So
the simple sense of לא תקיפו lo takifu means don't make a
circle like cut around your head, right, so that you circle off
your hair and it's like a continuous line. You can take a
line, you can take a string and go straight across and
your hair won't cross it. That's להקיף. leha'kif. So maybe when you
shave off all the hair and you're left bald, you're not being
מקיף, mekif, there's no circle hairline, there's no hairline. So this is
the question whether הקפת כל הראש שמה הקפה hakafat kol harosh shemah
hakafah is the prohibition of לא תקיפו. lo takifu. So שמואל Shmuel
could have just said okay, fine, you're an adult male and you
know why you're allowed to shave twice to be יוצא yotzei the
מצוה mitzvah of נזירות, neziros, even though we could have foregone the
second one, is because even if you are not a נזיר, even
if you're done with your נזירות, neziros? there's no real איסור דאורייתא
issur d'oraisa to shave
all the hair of your head. So why didn't שמואל Shmuel say
that? ונוקמה בגדול, venokmah begadol, why not say it and הקפת כל
הראש לא שמה הקפה, hakafat kol harosh lo shemah hakafah, and cutting
off all the hair of your head is not considered הקפה? hakafah?
מדלא מוקים לה הכי, midela mokim lah hachi, since he doesn't explain
it this way, שמע מינה קסבר שמואל, shema mina kasavar Shmuel, we
can infer from this that שמואל Shmuel is of the opinion הקפת
כל הראש שמה הקפה, hakafat kol harosh shemah hakafah, that would be
the prohibition.
That is very clear. Since שמואל Shmuel has to say we're talking
about a
woman who is not in the prohibition, it's clear that שמואל Shmuel
would understand that to shave if you are not obligated, if you're
not a נזיר, and if you're in the prohibition of shaving, to
shave all the hair of your head would be a violation. That
is very clear. שמואל Shmuel assumes that under normal circumstances it would
be a violation. So how do we let him shave twice? Why
do we let him do the shaving just to do the מצוה
mitzvah of נזירות? neziros It's not מעכב, me'akev, just to do the
מצוה mitzvah of נזירות if he might not need to shave the
second time? So you could either say it's not a violation to
shave all the hair of your head. שמואל Shmuel doesn't say that.
שמואל Shmuel says it's a special case of a woman who's not
in the prohibition. Okay, so we've seen this discussion before. Here it's
more fleshed out. So now the גמרא Gemara continues. מר זוטא מתני
לה להא שמעתא דשמואל אסיפא. Mar Zutra matni lah le-ha shema'ata de-Shmuel
asseifa. מר זוטא Mar Zutra has this discussion of שמואל Shmuel not
on our משנה, Mishnah but on a משנה coming up. And this
is a משנה we saw the other day. נזיר שהיה טמא בספק
ומצורע בספק. Nazir shehayah tamei besafek umetzora besafek. A נזיר that was
doubtful טומאת מת, tumas meis, doubtful מצורע. metzora. אוכל בקדשים לאחר ששים
יום, Ochel bekodashim le-achar shishim yom, he has to do 60 days
and brings all these various קרבנות korbanos at the end of each
30-day period. After 60 days, he's done with his צרעת tzara'as and
he can go ahead and eat קדשים. kodashim. ומגלח ארבע תגלחות, Umegaleiach
arba tiglachos, and he shaves four times because he's going to shave
at the end of each 30-day period, right, because he shaves as
a מצורע metzora he shaves at the end of when he starts
his process of טהרה taharah and then a week later when he
ends his process of טהרה taharah and a נזיר טמא nazir tamei
shaves at the end of his process of טומאה and at the
end of his process of טהרה, taharah, right? Is that clear? So
if you're both you'll have four shavings this guy's a ספק safek
so he has to spread them out by thirty days but ultimately
he's going to do four shavings. Okay but he would only have
needed four shavings if he genuinely was a מצורע metzora and a
נזיר טמא. nazir tamei. If he wasn't a מצורע metzora and wasn't
a נזיר טמא nazir tamei he only would have needed one shaving,
right? So what about the three extra shavings? How do we allow
that? Okay so הא קא עביד הקפה ha ka avid hakafah you're
doing the prohibition of shaving all the of the sideburns. אמר שמואל
amar Shmuel באשה וקטן be'ishah vekatan, fine we're talking about a woman
or a minor who's not in the prohibition. אמר רב הונא Amar
Rav Huna and then the question was ah so you see either
way that's how שמואל Shmuel deals with how do we allow this
shaving maybe maybe he's not obligated
and the other
answer obviously available answer was it's not the prohibition. Since שמואל Shmuel
doesn't say that you see שמואל Shmuel says that
this is the prohibition.
And so how do you get four cuttings instead of just sixty
days? A מצורע metzora has to when the צרעת tzara'at is the
כהן looks and it's cleared up he starts his process of טהרה
taharah by shaving and then he waits a week and he does
another shaving. Ah so that's after a week period after but we
wind up spacing it thirty days because he might be a not
מצורע metzora and yes a נזיר and whatever. And then as a
נזיר טמא nazir tamei he shaves and as a נזיר טהור nazir
tahor he shaves. Right so when he shaves as a נזיר after
thirty days and after sixty days he's already will have had some
shavings interim shavings as a מצורע metzora before that. I'm not going
to work through it again yesterday's דף daf we
worked through the whole logic I'm not going to do that again.
That's okay alright get notes from another student.
Alright so let's take
a look let's just do a little bit more. אמר רב הונא
המקיף את הקטן הרי הוא חייב. Amar Rav Huna hamakif et hakatan
harei hu chayav. So if somebody shaves a minor as opposed to
what שמואל Shmuel said that it seems to be that if the
kid is a if the shavee is a minor you're exempt he
says no if the shavee is a minor you're still חייב. chayav.
So here's the here's the conceptual issue that's going on here. The
תורה says לא תקיפו פאת ראשכם. lo takifu pe'at roshchem. So who's
it talking to? The shaver or the shavee? So פאת ראשכם pe'at
roshchem seems to be it's talking to the shavee don't cut off
your sideburns. But לא תקיפו lo takifu is talking to the shaver.
Now it might be you're doing both you're in you know you
go in the morning you take your shaver into the bathroom and
you're the shaver and the shavee.
Okay but the
question is which is the emphasis or are they independent? So when
רב הונא Rav Huna says that they're independent the shavee could be
exempt and out of the category and nevertheless you're the one doing
the shaving you're an adult so you're חייב. chayav. המקיף את הקטן
הרי הוא חייב Hamakif et hakatan harei hu chayav the shaver is
חייב chayav independent of the shavee. אמר ליה רב אדא בר אהבה
לרב הונא
ודידך מאן מגלח להו?
Amar lei Rav Adda bar Ahava le'Rav
Huna vedidach man megaleach lehu?
How about your kids? I see that your kids go around and
they've got their their sideburns cut off. How do you if you
say it's prohibited to shave the sideburns of a minor so who's
shaving your kids' sideburns? So אמר ליה חובה Amar lei Chovah my
wife because my wife is a woman and as a woman a
woman is excluded from the category. So what a woman can cut
a man's sideburns off? No because the man can't be the shavee.
The woman can be the shaver a minor can be the shavee
so if you combine a woman or a woman could be a
shaver so a woman or a minor can cut the hair of
a woman or a minor okay? But an adult male cannot cut
anybody's hair because he's prohibited as a shaver regardless of the shavee
and an adult male can't have his hair cut by anybody because
he's prohibited as the shavee. Okay but it's all about the adult
male. You can't have an adult male in either position but women
and minors you can. Is this רב הונא's Rav Huna wife's first
name? This is רב הונא's Rav Huna wife's first name חובה. Chovah.
So אמר ליה Amar lei so רב אדא בר אהבה Rav Adda
bar Ahava said to him חובה חובה Chovah Chovah I'm going to
call him חובה. Chovah. He said back to him תקברינהו חובה לבניה
tekavrinehu Chovah livneih so oh my God so he said
so חובה Chovah should you know should bury her children terrible thing
to say okay which basically means like oh my God how are
you letting your wife violate? Because he didn't agree with with his
position about this. We'll
explore tomorrow what his position was. Now the ראש Rosh softened it
a little bit. The ראש Rosh says because that sounds like you
know who would say such a thing. So the ראש Rosh makes
it rhetorical does she want to bury her children? Does she want
to cause them to transgress? How are you allowing this? So then
it says כולהו שני דרב אדא בר אהבה kulhu shenei de'Rav Adda
bar Ahava as long as רב אדא בר אהבה Rav Adda bar
Ahava who said that she should bury her children or was questioning
does she want to bury her children as long as he was
alive לא אוקים ליה זרע לרב הונא. lo okim lei zara le'Rav
Huna. רב הונא Rav Huna never had any more children. It didn't
say חובה Chovah never had any more children interesting it focuses on
רב הונא. Rav Huna. So there you go he said it and
even if he didn't mean it as a curse and even if
he meant it as an exclamation. Those words had power. Idea that's
very common in the גמרא. Gemara. But what we see here, tomorrow
we're going to explore the other opinion. What we see about רב
הונא's Rav Huna position is that it's the שווער shver and the
שבי shevi are independent. An adult male can't be a שווער shver
and can't be a שבי, shevi, but women and children can play
either role. And if an adult male is the שווער, shver, it
doesn't matter who the שבי shevi is, still transgresses. Now, I'll talk
more about that tomorrow. Okay, so we will end with this.